A heart-wrenching incident has come to light on the social media platform X.
In our country, health insurance is
considered a strong source of financial security
and people who pay huge premiums every year
expect the company to support them in times of need.
But after the
case of rejection of the claim of a person from Lucknow
came to light, questions have been raised on this trust also.
What is this whole
matter?  Look at the earlier understanding, it is being told
that the person was paying a
premium of around ₹00 every year for his mother's health policy.
When his mother fell ill,
for treatment he contacted the office of Star Health and
Allied Services Company, which you
know as Star Health, located
in Hazratganj, Lucknow.   The
allegation is that he was made to wait for several hours
and in the end his claim was
rejected.  Now Madam, this is a
matter of health insurance. We have discussed this many times
on our platform as well. This is a matter of great concern.
Madam, no matter how strongly it is condemned, there has been a
sharp reaction from many people on this news and this tweet.  People are saying
that Maharaj, you are doing it for ₹00.
I have been paying ₹80,000 premium for the last 8 years.
Suppose I have to go
in an emergency situation.  If my family
needs it, you will also reject it.
So what clarification has the company given on this now
?  Is this the whole matter?  A very deep
inside story.  Please explain this matter.
Whose responsibility is it?  These are the
companies that charge premiums.   The
premium of ₹00 is not less.  It is a
good amount of money.
This person from Lucknow was paying a premium of ₹00.
His mother was treated, which
cost him around Rs 4-5 lakh
and his videos in the company are
very disturbing.  This is a son who has been
paying premiums regularly
and when he
needed the insurance the most, the company said they
won't pay it. Why didn't the company pay it?
They say there is material non-disclosure
of facts, which means
they have hidden some of their illnesses. Material non-
disclosure means they have hidden such things, have
said misleading things, or have
hidden the fact of a pre-existing disease. If I
look at it officially,
what could be the material facts like a pre-
existing illness, a pre-existing disease, a
previous surgery, or you were hospitalized,
which you didn't disclose,
diabetes, BP, or any heart problem, or
you were taking any regular medication, which
you didn't disclose, and they
put the entire onus on the patient that
they hid the information. It is our
right because they have this clause of material
non-disclosure of facts,
due to which the companies have the right to
reject the insurance.
But I say that you should prove this,
you should just say in one line
that there is material non-disclosure, how will you prove this
?  When you gave the insurance, your
agent was selling the insurance to them.
No, listen, he asked for old details.   I apologize.
I am stopping you.
I am making a very meaningful statement, please
listen to it.  It was asked whether you had taken the policy after asking us
?  This
is not an official answer.  This is a verbal
conversation that is taking place between them.  The official
answer is.  Material non-disclosure of fact
which is why we are dismissing.  This
is a verbal answer.  Again, what do you see in this
?   The
sensitivity with which these
people sitting in the insurance office listen to you.
This is their sensitivity that you
took the insurance after asking us.  A person who has arrived is
saying that brother my mother is
ill.  I have to pay this amount for his operation.
Told him you are a liar.  You did this
and did you take insurance after asking us?
Brother, the company should have
a sensitivity among its employees to
see whether we are speaking and
listening, in such a situation
you are a public facing company.
Why do people take health insurance when others are in pain
?  He will need this insurance when he falls ill.
And when he falls ill and goes to
them with a hospitalization bill, they say,
brother, you have hidden things.  They are proving you a liar.
Okay, it is possible that we did
not know, we may not have been present there,
this gentleman is lying.  You should
prove that they are lying and
hence it is very important to complain against them.
But what happens to the complaints?   There
is a huge pile of complaints.  I am
looking at the statistics of Theme Insurance and
I want to put it before you
and this company which is currently
under the scanner is Star Health and Allied Insurance in the Lucknow case, there are
maximum complaints against it,
it is on top
in terms of complaints, 12186
complaints, now when we see
how many policies they have sold, they have sold 23780
policies, if we see that okay there are
12 lakh 12186 complaints then it will
seem less but there is a very interesting number
that how many complaints have come per lakh policy holders,
it is 51 and this is on the top
and Star Health, this is not the first time
that Star Health
is under the scanner of such allegations.  is surrounded by such questions.
Earlier also, Star Health was the company
which rejected the maximum number of
claims.  Therefore, their complaints are the
most prevalent in insurance objections.
Star Health was banned by hospitals in Gujarat.
Many hospitals in Delhi and Noida were
not accepting Star Health's policy.
I am telling this from my personal
experience.  Because
this company has the highest level of arbitrariness
and this is also being revealed by the figures of Om Babsman.
If Star Health is number one then I
would like to tell you number two and number three also
so that
people know that when you are taking insurance
and I am sorry to stop you again.   Please
tell me about this money because this ₹00, ₹80 is
not returned madam.  There are many such policies in
which if you deposit money and
pay premium, then at the time of maturity
you will
get that money back on the basis of cumulative compounding.  But
when we pay for health insurance,
we pay it throughout the year.
This money is not even returned.  And
when the need arises, suppose after 1 year or 2 years
or 5 years, if the need arises and at
that time you say that the claim should be rejected, then
₹50, suppose we
paid 5 lakhs for 10 years, then I lost it, then also
we will have to pay a bill of 5 lakhs, so
what is the point, why should we take insurance,
absolutely Star Health is number one
in this kind of arbitrariness and the name of the huge company at number two
is Care Health
Insurance, against which let's say it
is behind Star Health, 4400 complaints, yes it is one
third among them also, but out of every 1 lakh of their
policy holders, 17 people have
complained and on the third number
is Neeva Bupa Health Insurance and these
figures which I am reading, let me tell you, this is the
Annual
Report 20425 of the Council of Insurance Obbudsmen, it has been published in ERDA's Handbook on
Indian Insurance Statistics 20425 so that no
one should ask
where I have brought these figures from.  These
figures are printed in the IRDAI handbook.
Madam, these figures and many other things from there must have remained unwritten.
Many people might be silently thinking that they should give it now.
What should I do brother, there is so much
commotion, what video should I make?
These are just a few such videos that are going
viral.  Otherwise, just imagine how many
claims have been rejected and
this video has gone viral.  We don't know yet whether this Janam has
lodged his complaint
or not.  They should
definitely go to the insurance man.
Internally also, these insurance companies have their
own complaint grievance redressal
mechanisms.  But frankly I do
n't trust him.
Still, it is my duty, Madam, to tell
my viewers
how IRDAI can help you because you
must also have health insurance.  You
people might have also taken it.  The way
medical costs seem to be increasing.
Every middle class person wants to at
least insure his own health and that of his family.  There
are some two or three options.  I am telling you.
If needed, you can use it.
Visit the online portal of the ad, Bima Bharosa System.  There, on the top left side, you
will see the option of Register Complaint.
Click on it and fill in the correct information.
So after that your problem can be
solved.  Apart from that,
you can also register your complaint through email at complaints@.gov.in.  There is
also a toll free number,
I will tell you that also.
You can also register your complaint by calling 15525 or 188004254732.
So Madam, as many
things as I said,
but before registering a complaint here,
Vishal is the first point of escalation with the
company.  Ilda ho insurance
ambsman ho.  Apart from these two steps, you
can also approach the Insurance Ombudsman.  But
before that you will have to prove that you
sent your complaint to the company.  Either the company has
not taken any action or
you are not satisfied with the action taken by the company and after that
you are taking it to IRDAI in the escalation matrix.
But the big
but is whether the complaints are being heard quickly enough in the Insurance Ombudsman
and this is a big factor.  We
say in our country that the reach of insurance
, the penetration of insurance
, is very low.  Why is it less?  All these
incidents, when you have to spend from your own pocket, then
we should
not do that, brother, first
pay the premium and when you get into trouble, then
you should pay the bill for your expenses as well, that is what
I am saying,
even after paying the insurance, if I have to spend from my own pocket, then
why should I take such insurance, what is the use of it,
which is not helping me in my difficult times,
and then we sit with the data
and we say that the
reach of insurance is very low in India.  People are
not buying insurance because these insurance
companies are acting arbitrarily like this.
That is why people shy away from buying insurance thinking
that if they let me pay the premium,
my hair will turn grey
and when I will need that insurance,
I know many people who
pay the premium through EMI
and you say that I also
look at the balance sheets of the companies.  Companies say that there is
immense business potential.   If
penetration is very low then there is immense potential.
So improve yourself as well.  There
is immense business potential but there is
no scope for accountability.  Why do
n't companies come forward and respond?  Star Health
just issued a hollow statement that the
material was non-disclosure.  I don't
think I am not satisfied.  I think the
company should tell what they have
hidden.  You can't tell me why.
You will tell me when he reaches IRDAI.
You will tell us when this reaches the Insurance Ombudsman.
Why?  You have taken money from me.
I have given you money.
This is your responsibility.  It is my right to know
that if I have given you money then
why will you say that
you took the insurance after asking us.  If you want to give this answer
then send the policy,
Indian consumer will also reply to you that he will not
buy it.